3-42, Athabasca Hall, Edmonton, Alberta, T6G 2E8, Canada

Research Areas

My primary research interest is to develop and evaluate various program analysis techniques that can be used in practice by exploring three aspects: scalability, precision, and usability. My interests span programming languages and software systems.

Education

Ph.D., Computer Science

2014

University of Waterloo, Canada

- · Advisor: Ondřej Lhoták
- Thesis: The Separate Compilation Assumption
- · Committee: Jan Vitek, Frank Tip, Reid Holmes, and Werner Dietl

MMath, Computer Science

2010

University of Waterloo, Canada

- · Advisor: Raouf Boutaba
- Thesis: Algorizmi A Configurable Virtual Testbed to Generate Datasets for Offline Evaluation of Intrusion Detection Systems
- Reviewers: Ian MacKillop and Urs Hengartner

B.Sc., Computer Science

2007

THE AMERICAN UNIVERSITY IN CAIRO, EGYPT

- · Advisors: Sherif G. Aly and Sherif El-Kassas
- Thesis: A Jabber Framework for Building Communication Capable Java Mobile Applications
- · Minor: Mathematics

Professional Experience

Assistant Professor, Department of Computing Science

Jul 2017-Present

University of Alberta, Canada

Research Assistant Professor, Department of Computing Science

Jul 2016-Jul 2017

University of Alberta, Canada

Postdoctoral Researcher, Secure Software Engineering

Oct 2014–Jul 2016

TECHNISCHE UNIVERSITÄT DARMSTADT, GERMANY

- Host: Eric Bodden
- Designing novel static analyses to detect misuses of cryptographic APIs in software systems
- Exploring new static analysis techniques that incorporate user feedback in a just-in-time fashion
- · Developing various extensions to the IFDS analysis framework

Graduate Research Assistant, Programming Languages Group

2010-2014

University of Waterloo, Canada

- Conducted research for constructing partial static call graphs for Java programs
- Developed various call graph construction algorithms for Scala
- Studied static analysis techniques for various JVM-hosted languages

Graduate Research Assistant, Network Security Research Group

2008-2009

University of Waterloo, Canada

- · Worked on various models of Intrusion Detection Systems: e.g., peer-to-peer, kernel methods
- Developed Algorizmi, an open-source evaluation system for Intrusion Detection Systems

Researcher, Department of Computer Science

2007

THE AMERICAN UNIVERSITY IN CAIRO, EGYPT

• Studied new techniques to support location management in Java-based pervasive systems

MAY 15, 2019 KARIM ALI · CURRICULUM VITAE 1/6

ITWORX, EGYPT

• Redesigned the graphical user interface of the stock brokerage system for Execution Ltd., London, UK

Awards and Honors _____

Awards and Honors	
ACM SIGPLAN Distinguished Paper Award ACM SIGPLAN SYMPOSIUM ON PRINCIPLES OF PROGRAMMING LANGUAGES	2019
Student's Choice Award University of Alberta	2018
ACM SIGSOFT Distinguished Paper Award International Symposium on Software Testing and Analysis	2017
Distinguished Artifact Award EUROPEAN CONFERENCE ON OBJECT-ORIENTED PROGRAMMING	2014
David R. Cheriton Scholarship UNIVERSITY OF WATERLOO, CANADA	2012–2014 \$20,000
Special Graduate Scholarship UNIVERSITY OF WATERLOO, CANADA	2012 \$2,500
Queen Elizabeth II Graduate Scholarship in Science and Technology CANADA	2012 \$5,000
Special Graduate Scholarship UNIVERSITY OF WATERLOO, CANADA	2011 \$1,000
Graduate Entrance Scholarship UNIVERSITY OF WATERLOO, CANADA	2008 \$3,000
B.Sc. Summa Cum Laude Honors The American University in Cairo, Egypt	2007
Best CS Group Graduation Project Award THE AMERICAN UNIVERSITY IN CAIRO, EGYPT	2007
Shell Endowed Scholarship The American University in Cairo, Egypt	2003–2007 30% off tuition

Professional Service _____

PROGRAM COMMITTEE ORGANIZATION

PLMW Co-Chair, ACM SIGPLAN Conference on Systems, Programming, Languages and Applications: Software for Humanity (SPLASH)	2019
SPLASH-I Co-Chair, ACM SIGPLAN Conference on Systems, Programming, Languages and Applications: Software for Humanity (SPLASI	H) 2018
SPLASH-I Co-Chair, ACM SIGPLAN Conference on Systems, Programming, Languages and Applications: Software for Humanity (SPLASI	H) 2017
Artifact Evaluation Co-Chair, International Symposium on Engineering Secure Software and Systems (ESSoS)	2017
Demonstration Track Co-Chair, ACM SIGSOFT Symposium on the Foundations of Software Engineering (FSE)	2017
Program Committee Co-Chair, ACM SIGPLAN International Workshop on the State Of the Art in Program Analysis (SOAP) @ PLDI	2017

PROGRAM COMMITTEE MEMBER

ISSTA, International Symposium on Software Testing and Analysis	2019
SOAP @ PLDI, ACM SIGPLAN International Workshop on the State Of the Art in Program Analysis	2019
ECOOP, European Conference on Object-Oriented Programming	2018
ISSTA, International Symposium on Software Testing and Analysis	2018
CASCON, International Conference on Computer Science and Software Engineering	2017
Onward! ACM International Symposium on New Ideas, New Paradigms, and Reflections on Programming and Software	2017

ARTIFACT EVALUATION COMMITTEE MEMBER	
ISSTA, International Symposium on Software Testing and Analysis PLDI, ACM SIGPLAN Conference on Programming Language Design and Implementation ECOOP, European Conference on Object-Oriented Programming ECOOP, European Conference on Object-Oriented Programming	2016 2015 2015 2014
Workshop Organization	
Co-Organizer, Program Analysis Hackathon (Panathon) @ ECOOP/ISSTA Co-Organizer, Workshop on Benchmarking (BenchWork) @ ECOOP/ISSTA Co-Organizer, Compiler-Driven Performance Workshop @ CASCON Co-Organizer, SOAP @ PLDI Co-Organizer, WALA Hackathon @ PLDI Co-Organizer, Workshop on Designing Code Analysis Frameworks (DECAF) @ ISSTA Co-Organizer, Workshop on WALA @ PLDI	2018 2018 2017 2017 2017 2016 2015
Reviewer	
TSE, IEEE Transactions on Software Engineering TOPLAS, ACM Transactions on Programming Languages and Systems SCP, Science of Computer Programming	2013, 2019 2018, 2019 2015
OTHER	
Steering Committee Member, Undergraduate Capstone Open Source Projects (UCOSP) Faculty Mentor, Undergraduate Capstone Open Source Projects (UCOSP) Associate Editor, IEEE Software Blog Web Chair, European Conference on Object-Oriented Programming (ECOOP) Web Chair, International Symposium on Software Testing and Analysis (ISSTA) Subreviewer, International Conference on Compiler Construction (CC)	2018 2018 2017–Present 2018 2018 2017
Research Funding	

Validating the Correct Usage of Cryptography Libraries

2018-2020

- IBM Centre for Advanced Studies Research Fellowship
- With: Sole PI
- Amount: CAD\$60,000

Scalable and Precise Program Analysis for Modern Software Systems

2017-2022

- Natural Sciences and Engineering Research Council of Canada (NSERC) Discovery Grant
- With: Sole PI
- Amount: CAD\$125,000

Improving the Inlining Algorithms in the IBM Just-in-Time (JIT) Compiler

2017-2020

- IBM Centre for Advanced Studies Research Fellowship
- · With: Sole PI
- · Amount: CAD\$90.000

Publications

REFEREED JOURNAL ARTICLES

Johannes Späth, Karim Ali, and Eric Bodden. "Context-, Flow-, and Field-Sensitive Data-Flow Analysis Using Synchronized Pushdown Systems". PACMPL, 3(POPL), 48:1-48:29, 2019.

POPL '19 Distinguished Paper

Lisa Nguyen Quang Do, Stefan Krüger, Patrick Hill, Karim Ali, and Eric Bodden. "Debugging Static Analysis". IEEE Transactions on Software Engineering, (to appear), 2018.

TSF '18

Johannes Späth, **Karim Ali**, and Eric Bodden. "IDE^{al}: Efficient and Precise Alias-Aware Dataflow Analysis". *PACMPL*, OOPSLA '17 1(OOPSLA), 99:1–99:27, 2017. Karim Ali, Marianna Rapoport, Ondřej Lhoták, Julian Dolby, and Frank Tip. "Type-Based Call Graph Construction TOSEM '15 Algorithms for Scala". ACM Transactions on Software Engineering and Methodology, 25(1), 9:1–9:43, 2015. Sherif Aly, Sarah Nadi, and Karim Hamdan. "A Java-Based Programming Language Support of Location Manage-IJCSNS '08 ment in Pervasive Systems". International Journal of Computer Science and Network Security, 8(6), pp. 329–336, 2008. REFERED CONFERENCE PUBLICATIONS Stefan Krüger, Johannes Späth, Karim Ali, Eric Bodden, and Mira Mezini. "CrySL: An Extensible Approach to Val-**ECOOP** '18 idating the Correct Usage of Cryptographic APIs". European Conference on Object-Oriented Programming, 10:1-10:27, 2018. Lisa Nguyen Quang Do, Stefan Krüger, Patrick Hill, Karim Ali, and Eric Bodden. "VISUFLOW: A Debugging Envi-ICSE '18 ronment for Static Analyses". International Conference on Software Engineering (Companion Volume), pp. 89–92, Tool Paper 2018. Stefan Krüger, Sarah Nadi, Michael Reif, Karim Ali, Mira Mezini, Eric Bodden, Florian Göpfert, Felix Günther, Chris-ASE '17 tian Weinert, Daniel Demmler, and Ram Kamath. "CogniCrypt: Supporting Developers in using Cryptography". Tool Paper *International Conference on Automated Software Engineering*, pp. 931–936, 2017. Mona Nashaat, Karim Ali, and James Miller. "Detecting Security Vulnerabilities in Object-Oriented PHP Programs". SCAM '17 IEEE International Working Conference on Source Code Analysis and Manipulation, pp. 159–164, 2017. Taylor Lloyd, Artem Chikin, Erick Ochoa, Karim Ali, and J Nelson Amaral. "A Case for Better Integration of Host and FSP '17 Target Compilation When Using OpenCL for FPGAs". International Workshop on FPGAs for Software Programmers, pp. 1–9, 2017. Lisa Nguyen Quang Do, Karim Ali, Ben Livshits, Eric Bodden, Justin Smith, and Emerson Murphy-Hill. "Just-in-ISSTA '17 Time Static Analysis". International Symposium on Software Testing and Analysis, pp. 307–317, 2017. Distinguished Paper Lisa Nguyen Quang Do, Karim Ali, Ben Livshits, Eric Bodden, Justin Smith, and Emerson Murphy-Hill. "Cheetah: ICSE '17 Just-in-Time Taint Analysis for Android Apps". International Conference on Software Engineering - Companion Vol-Tool Paper ume, pp. 39-42, 2017. Johannes Späth, Lisa Nguyen Quang Do, Karim Ali, and Eric Bodden. "Boomerang: Demand-Driven Flow-**ECOOP** '16 Sensitive, Field-Sensitive, and Context-Sensitive Pointer Analysis". European Conference on Object-Oriented Programming, 22:1-22:26, 2016. Steven Arzt, Sarah Nadi, Karim Ali, Eric Bodden, Sebastian Erdweg, and Mira Mezini. "Towards Secure Integration Onward! '15 of Cryptographic Software". ACM SIGPLAN Symposium on New Ideas in Programming and Reflections on Software at SPLASH, pp. 1-13, 2015. Karim Ali, Marianna Rapoport, Ondřej Lhoták, Julian Dolby, and Frank Tip. "Constructing Call Graphs of Scala ECOOP '14 Programs". European Conference on Object-Oriented Programming, pp. 54–79, 2014. Distinguished Artifact Karim Ali and Ondřej Lhoták. "Averroes: Whole-Program Analysis without the Whole Program". European Confer-**ECOOP** '13 ence on Object-Oriented Programming, pp. 378-400, 2013. Karim Ali and Ondřej Lhoták. "Application-Only Call Graph Construction". European Conference on Object-Oriented ECOOP '12 Programming, pp. 688-712, 2012. OTHER REFEREED PUBLICATIONS Karim Ali, Issam Aib, and Raouf Boutaba. "P2P-AIS: A P2P Artificial Immune Systems architecture for detecting GIIS '09 DDoS flooding attacks". Global Information Infrastructure Symposium, 2009. Karim Ali and Raouf Boutaba. "Applying Kernel Methods to Anomaly-based Intrusion Detection Systems". Global GIIS '09 Information Infrastructure Symposium, 2009.

Students_

CURRENT

Ifaz Kabir 2018–Present

University of Alberta, Canada Ph.D.

Abdul Ali Bangash 2018–Present

University of Alberta, Canada, (main supervisor; co-supervised with Abram Hindle)

Ph.D.

Kristen Newbury 2018–Present

University of Alberta, Canada Master's

Erick Ochoa 2017–Present

University of Alberta, Canada, (main supervisor; co-supervised with José Nelson Amaral)

Master's

Stefan Krüger 2015–Present

University of Paderborn, Germany, (co-supervised with Eric Bodden)

Ph.D.

Lisa Nguyen 2015–Present

University of Paderborn, Germany, (co-supervised with Eric Bodden)

Ph.D.

ALUMNI

Johannes Späth 2019

University of Paderborn, Germany, (co-supervised with Eric Bodden)

Research Associate at Fraunhofer IEM

• Ph.D. Thesis: Synchronized Pushdown Systems for Pointer and Data-Flow Analysis

Manuel Benz 2016

TECHNISCHE UNIVERSITÄT DARMSTADT, GERMANY

Master's Thesis: Interprocedural Data Dependency Graphs

Ph.D. at University of Paderborn

Michael Appel 2016

TECHNISCHE UNIVERSITÄT DARMSTADT, GERMANY

• Master's Thesis: Call Graph Summaries for the Android SDK

Teaching_

INSTRUCTOR

CMPUT 497	Foundations of Program Analysis, University of Alberta, Canada	Winter 2019-Present
CMPUT 229	Computer Organization and Architecture I, University of Alberta, Canada	Winter 2017-Present
CMPUT 620	Static Program Analysis, University of Alberta, Canada	Fall 2016–Present
SAS	Static Analysis Seminar, Technische Universität Darmstadt, Germany	Winter 2015

Co-Instructor

APSA Applied Static Analysis, Technische Universität Darmstadt, Germany Spring 2016

SUBSTITUTE LECTURER

DECA	Designing Code Analyses for Large Software Systems, Technische Universität Darmstadt, Germany	Winter 2014
CS 241	Foundations of Sequential Programs, University of Waterloo, Canada	Spring 2013

GRADUATE TEACHING ASSISTANT

CS 241	Foundations of Sequential Programs, University of Waterloo, Canada	2011–2013
CS 444/644	Compiler Construction, University of Waterloo, Canada	2011–2013
CS 446/646	Software Design and Architectures, University of Waterloo, Canada	Spring 2011
CS 456/656	Computer Networks, University of Waterloo, Canada	2008–2010
CS 125	Introduction to Programming Principles, University of Waterloo, Canada	Winter 2008
CS 448	Security Engineering, The American University in Cairo, Egypt	Fall 2007

Undergraduate Teaching Assistant

CS 448	Security Engineering, The American University in Cairo, Egypt	Fall 2007
CS 330	Computer Architecture, The American University in Cairo, Egypt	2005–2006
CS 106	Fundamentals of Computer Science, The American University in Cairo, Egypt	2004–2005

Volunteer Work _____

Reverse EXPO Co-Organizer, University of Alberta, Canada	2018-Present
CyberPatriot Technical Mentor, Strathcona High School, Edmonton, Alberta, Canada	2016–2018
Graduate Student Ambassador, University of Waterloo, Canada	Fall 2013
Tour Guide, Computer Science Open House, University of Waterloo, Canada	Winter 2012
President, Egyptian Students Association, University of Waterloo, Canada	2010–2011
Ushers Committee Leader, Honors Assembly, The American University in Cairo, Egypt	Spring 2007
Academic Committee Head, ACM Chapter, The American University in Cairo, Egypt	Spring 2007